I admit that I'm a little bit nervous here
أعترف أنني مرتبك قليلا هنا
because I'm going to say some radical things,
لأنني سأقوم بقول بعض الأشياء المتطرفة
about how we should think about cancer differently,
عن كيف يتوجب علينا أن نفكر بالسرطان بطريقة مختلفة
to an audience that contains a lot of people
لجمهور يحتوي الكثير من الناس
who know a lot more about cancer than I do.
الذين يعرفون عن السرطان أكثر مني.
But I will also contest that I'm not as nervous as I should be
لكن سأعترف بأنني لست مرتبكا بالقدر الذي يفترض علي أن أكونه
because I'm pretty sure I'm right about this.
لأنني متأكد جدا أنني على حق بهذا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And that this, in fact, will be
و هذه هي، بالفعل، ستكون
the way that we treat cancer in the future.
الطريقة التي نعالج فيها السرطان في المستقبل.
In order to talk about cancer,
من أجل الحديث عن السرطان،
I'm going to actually have to --
سأقوم بالفعل بعمل --
let me get the big slide here.
دعوني أحضر الشريحة الكبيرة هنا.
First, I'm going to try to give you a different perspective of genomics.
أولا، سأحاول أن أعطيكم منظورا مختلفا لعلم الجينوم (علم دراسة كامل المادة الوراثية)
I want to put it in perspective of the bigger picture
أريد أن أضعه بمنظور الصورة العامة
of all the other things that are going on --
لكل الأمور الأخرى التي تجري --
and then talk about something you haven't heard so much about, which is proteomics.
و بعدها أتحدث عن شئ لم تسمعوا عنه الكثير، الذي هو البروتيوميات (دراسة أنواع البروتينات).
Having explained those,
بكوني فسرت هذين،
that will set up for what I think will be a different idea
سوف يمهد لما أظن أنه سيكون فكرة مختلفة
about how to go about treating cancer.
عن كيف سنقوم بعلاج السرطان.
So let me start with genomics.
دعوني أبدأ بعلم الجينوم.
It is the hot topic.
إنه موضوع متداول.
It is the place where we're learning the most.
إنه أكثر مكان نتعلم منه.
This is the great frontier.
إنه عظيم الحدود.
But it has its limitations.
لكن لديه قيوده.
And in particular, you've probably all heard the analogy
و بالتحديد، كلكم من الممكن أنكم سمعتم عن المماثلة
that the genome is like the blueprint of your body,
التي هي علم الجينوم هو مثل المخططات الأولية لأجسامكم.
and if that were only true, it would be great,
و لو كانت فقط صحيحة، سيكون رائعا،
but it's not.
لكنها ليست كذلك.
It's like the parts list of your body.
إنها كقائمة أعضاء أجسامكم.
It doesn't say how things are connected,
إنها لا تقول كيف تترابط الأشياء،
what causes what and so on.
ماذا يسبب الآخر و هكذا.
So if I can make an analogy,
و إذا كان باستطاعتي وضع مقاربة،
let's say that you were trying to tell the difference
سنقل أنكم تحاولون إيجاد الفرق
between a good restaurant, a healthy restaurant
بين مطعم جيد، مطعم صحي،
and a sick restaurant,
و مطعم مريض،
and all you had was the list of ingredients
و كل ما كان بحوزتكم هو قائمة المقادير
that they had in their larder.
التي لديهم في حافظتهم.
So it might be that, if you went to a French restaurant
فقد يكون أن، إذا ذهبتم إلى مطعم فرنسي
and you looked through it and you found
و بحثتم لتجدوا أن
they only had margarine and they didn't have butter,
لديهم فقط السمنة الصناعسة و ليس لديهم زبدة،
you could say, "Ah, I see what's wrong with them.
قد تقولون، "آه، رأينا ما هي مشكلتهم.
I can make them healthy."
أستطيع أن أجعلهم صحيين."
And there probably are special cases of that.
و قد تكون هناك حالات خاصة لهذا.
You could certainly tell the difference
تستطيعون بالتأكيد معرفة الفرق
between a Chinese restaurant and a French restaurant
بين مطعم صيني و مطعم فرنسي
by what they had in a larder.
عن طريق معرفة مالديهم في حافظتهم.
So the list of ingredients does tell you something,
فقائمة المقادير تخبركم بشئ،
and sometimes it tells you something that's wrong.
و أحيانا تخبركم بشئ خاطئ.
If they have tons of salt,
لو كان لديهم الكثير من الملح،
you might guess they're using too much salt, or something like that.
قد تخمنون أنهم يستعملون الكثير من الملح، و شيئا من هذا القبيل.
But it's limited,
لكن هذا قاصر،
because really to know if it's a healthy restaurant,
لأنكم لتعرفوا بالفعل أنه مطعم صحي،
you need to taste the food, you need to know what goes on in the kitchen,
يجب عليكم أن تتذوقوا الطعام، يجب أن تعرفوا ما يدور في المطبخ،
you need the product of all of those ingredients.
تحتاجون منتوج كل هذه المقادير.
So if I look at a person
فلو نظرت إلى إنسان
and I look at a person's genome, it's the same thing.
و نظرت إلى جنيوم هذا الإنسان، إنهما الشئ نفسه.
The part of the genome that we can read
جزء الجنيوم الذي باستطاعتنا قرآته
is the list of ingredients.
هو قائمة المقادير.
And so indeed,
و في الواقع،
there are times when we can find ingredients
هناك أوقات نجد فيها مقادير
that [are] bad.
سيئة.
Cystic fibrosis is an example of a disease
التليف الكيسي هو مثال لمرض
where you just have a bad ingredient and you have a disease,
الذي يكون لديكم أحد المقادير السيئة التي تسبب المرض،
and we can actually make a direct correspondence
و يمكن أن نكون علاقات مباشرة بين
between the ingredient and the disease.
أحد المقادير و المرض.
But most things, you really have to know what's going on in the kitchen,
لكن معظم الأشياء، يجب أن نعرف بالفعل ما يدون بالمطبخ،
because, mostly, sick people used to be healthy people --
لأن، في الغالبية، الناس المريضين كانو أناسا أصحاء --
they have the same genome.
لديهم نفس الجنيوم.
So the genome really tells you much more
فالجنيوم يخبركم فعلا الكثير
about predisposition.
عن التركيب الوراثي.
So what you can tell
فما تستطيعون معرفته
is you can tell the difference between an Asian person and a European person
هو أن يكون بمقدرتكم معرفته الفرق بين الشخص الآسيوي و الشخص الأوربي
by looking at their ingredients list.
بالنظر فقط إلى قائمة مقاديرهم.
But you really for the most part can't tell the difference
لكن في معظم الأوقات لا تستطيعون معرفة الفرق
between a healthy person and a sick person --
بين شخص مريض و شخص صحيح--
except in some of these special cases.
فقط في بعض هذه الحالات الخاصة.
So why all the big deal
فماهي أهمية
about genetics?
علم الوراثة؟
Well first of all,
حسنا قبل كل شئ,
it's because we can read it, which is fantastic.
لأننا نستطيع قرأتها, و هو أمر هائل.
It is very useful in certain circumstances.
إنه عملي جدا في حالات معينة.
It's also the great theoretical triumph
إنه أيضا الانتصار النظري الرائع
of biology.
لعلم الأحياء.
It's the one theory
إنها النظرية الوحيدة
that the biologists ever really got right.
التي عرف علماء الأحياء صحتها.
It's fundamental to Darwin
إنها أساسية لداروين
and Mendel and so on.
و مندل و غيرهم.
And so it's the one thing where they predicted a theoretical construct.
و إنها الشئ الوحيد الذي توقعوا فيه صنع نظرية.
So Mendel had this idea of a gene
مندل كانت لديه فكرة الجين
as an abstract thing,
كشئ مجرد.
and Darwin built a whole theory
و دارون بني نظرية بأكملها
that depended on them existing,
مبنية على وجودها.
and then Watson and Crick
و من ثم واستن و كريك
actually looked and found one.
فعلا بحثوا و وجدوا واحدة.
So this happens in physics all the time.
فهذا يحصل في الفيزياء كل الوقت.
You predict a black hole,
فأنت تتنبأ بثقب أسود,
and you look out the telescope and there it is, just like you said.
و تنظر عبر التلسكوب لتجده, مثلما قلت.
But it rarely happens in biology.
لكن نادرا ما يحدث هذا في علم الأحياء.
So this great triumph -- it's so good,
فهذا انتصار رائع --إنه جيد--
there's almost a religious experience
هناك تقريبا خبرة عقائدية
in biology.
في علم الأحياء.
And Darwinian evolution
و نظرية التطور لداروين
is really the core theory.
هي فعلا النظرية الأساسية.
So the other reason it's been very popular
و السبب الآخر لكونها مشهورة
is because we can measure it, it's digital.
لأننا نستطيع قياسها, إنها رقمية.
And in fact,
و في الواقع,
thanks to Kary Mullis,
الشكر لكاري موليس,
you can basically measure your genome in your kitchen
نتسطيع قياس الجنيوم في مطابخنا
with a few extra ingredients.
بزبادة بعض المقادير.
So for instance, by measuring the genome,
فعلى سبيل المثال, بمقياسنا للجنيوم
we've learned a lot about how we're related to other kinds of animals
فتعلمنا الكثير عن صلتنا بأنواع الحيوانات
by the closeness of our genome,
عن طريق تقارب الجنيوم,
or how we're related to each other -- the family tree,
أو كيف نتصل ببعضنا البعض-- شجرة العائلة,
or the tree of life.
أو شجرة الحياة.
There's a huge amount of information about the genetics
هناك كم هائل من المعلومات عن الجينات
just by comparing the genetic similarity.
فقط بمقارنة تشابه الجينات.
Now of course, in medical application,
الآن بالطبع, في التطبيقات الطبية,
that is very useful
هذا جدا مفيد
because it's the same kind of information
لأنها نفس نوع المعلومات
that the doctor gets from your family medical history --
التي يحصل عليها الطبيب من تاريخ العائلة الطبي --
except probably,
ربما باستثناء,
your genome knows much more about your medical history than you do.
الجنيوم يعرف تاريخ عائلتك الطبي أكثر مما تعرفه أنت.
And so by reading the genome,
و بقراءة الجنبيوم,
we can find out much more about your family than you probably know.
ربما نتسطيع معرفة الكثير عن عائلتك مما تعرفه أنت.
And so we can discover things
و نتسطيع اكتشاف أشياء
that probably you could have found
التي ربما قد عرفتها
by looking at enough of your relatives,
عبر نظرك إلى أقرابئك,
but they may be surprising.
و لكن قد تكون مفاجآة.
I did the 23andMe thing
عملت التجربة على نفسي
and was very surprised to discover that I am fat and bald.
و تفآجأت جدا لأكتشف بأنني سمين و أصلع.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But sometimes you can learn much more useful things about that.
لكن أحيانا تستطيع معرفة أشياء مقيدة أكثر بكثير عن هذا.
But mostly
لكن غالبا
what you need to know, to find out if you're sick,
ما تحتاج معرفته لتكتشف إن كنت مريضا
is not your predispositions,
هو ليس ميل جسمك لتكوين المرض,
but it's actually what's going on in your body right now.
لكن فعليا هو ما يحدث في جسمك الآن.
So to do that, what you really need to do,
و لعمل هذا, ما تحتاج حقا فعله هو,
you need to look at the things
تحتاج النظر إلى الأشياء
that the genes are producing
التي تنتجها الجينات
and what's happening after the genetics,
و ما يحدث بعد الجينات.
and that's what proteomics is about.
و هذا هو دور البروتيوميات.
Just like genome mixes the study of all the genes,
مثلما ما يخلط الجنيوم دراسة كل الجينات,
proteomics is the study of all the proteins.
البروتيوميات هو دراسة كل البروتينات.
And the proteins are all of the little things in your body
و البروتيوميات هي كل الأشياء الصغيرة في جسمك
that are signaling between the cells --
التي تؤدي إلى إشارات بين الخلايا--
actually, the machines that are operating --
في الواقع هي الآلات العاملة.
that's where the action is.
و هنا تكمن الحركة.
Basically, a human body
أساسا, جسم الإنسان
is a conversation going on,
هو محاورة مستمرة,
both within the cells and between the cells,
داخل الخلايا و بين الخلايا,
and they're telling each other to grow and to die,
و هم يطلبون من بعضهم البعض النمو و الموت.
and when you're sick,
و عندما تمرض,
something's gone wrong with that conversation.
يحدث خطأ ما في هذه المحاورة.
And so the trick is --
و الفكرة هي--
unfortunately, we don't have an easy way to measure these
للأسف, ليست هناك طريقة سهلة لقياس هذه
like we can measure the genome.
مثل التي نقيس فيها الجنيوم.
So the problem is that measuring --
فالمشكلة هي ذلك القياس--
if you try to measure all the proteins, it's a very elaborate process.
لو جربت أن تقيس كل البروتينات, فإنها عملية جدا معقدة.
It requires hundreds of steps,
إنها تتطلب مئات الخطوات,
and it takes a long, long time.
و تأخذ وقتا طويلا جدا.
And it matters how much of the protein it is.
و مقدار البروتين المتواجد ذو أهمية.
It could be very significant that a protein changed by 10 percent,
قد يكون ذا أهمية كبيرة إذا تغير البروتين بنسبة 10 في المائة,
so it's not a nice digital thing like DNA.
فهي ليست الدي إن أي الرقمية اللطيفة.
And basically our problem is somebody's in the middle
و أساسا مشكلتنا هي وجود أحدهم في وسط
of this very long stage,
هذه المرحلة الطويلة,
they pause for just a moment,
يتوقفون فقط للحظة,
and they leave something in an enzyme for a second,
و يتركون شيئا في الأنزيم لثانية,
and all of a sudden all the measurements from then on
و فجأة كل القياسات بعد هذا
don't work.
لا تعمل.
And so then people get very inconsistent results
و بهذا يجد الناس نتائج غير متناسقة
when they do it this way.
حين يعملون بهذه الطريقة.
People have tried very hard to do this.
الناس حاولوا بتصميم لعمل هذا.
I tried this a couple of times
أنا حاولت هذا مرتين
and looked at this problem and gave up on it.
و نظرت إلى هذه المشكلة و تخليت عنها.
I kept getting this call from this oncologist
أتتني اتصالات مستمرة من طبيب أورام
named David Agus.
اسمه دايفد أوقس.
And Applied Minds gets a lot of calls
و "أبلايد مايندز" تصلها اتصالات كثيرة
from people who want help with their problems,
من أناس يريدون مساعدة في مشاكلهم,
and I didn't think this was a very likely one to call back,
و أنا لم أظن أن هناك احتمالا أن هذا الشخص سيعيد الاتصال,
so I kept on giving him to the delay list.
فاستمريت اضعه على قائمة التأجيل.
And then one day,
و في يوم ما,
I get a call from John Doerr, Bill Berkman
وصلني اتصال من جون دوير, بيل بركمان
and Al Gore on the same day
و أل قور في نفس اليوم
saying return David Agus's phone call.
يقولون رد على اتصال ديفيد أوقس.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So I was like, "Okay. This guy's at least resourceful."
و كنت أفكر "حسنا. على الأقل هذا رجل واصل."
So we started talking,
فبدأنا نتكلم,
and he said, "I really need a better way to measure proteins."
و قال, " أنا فعلا أحتاج طريقة أفضل لقياس البروتينات."
I'm like, "Looked at that. Been there.
و أنا كنت مثل, "انظر إلى هذا. لقد كنت هناك.
Not going to be easy."
لن يكون سهلا."
He's like, "No, no. I really need it.
و هو كان يقول " لا لا . أنا فعلا بحاجة لها.
I mean, I see patients dying every day
قصدي, إني أرى مرضى يموتون كل يوم
because we don't know what's going on inside of them.
لأننا لا نعرف ما يدور في داخلهم.
We have to have a window into this."
يتوجب علينا أن نجد منفذا لهذا."
And he took me through
و أخذنا عبر
specific examples of when he really needed it.
أمثلة معينة للأوقات التي كان فعلا بحاجة إليها.
And I realized, wow, this would really make a big difference,
بعدها استوعبت, تعجبت, إن هذا سيحدث فعلا فرقا كبيرا
if we could do it,
لو استطعنا فعله.
and so I said, "Well, let's look at it."
ثم قلت, "حسنا, لننظر إليها."
Applied Minds has enough play money
أبلايد مايندز لديها نقود كافية للتجارب
that we can go and just work on something
نستطيع أن نقوم بالعمل على أمر ما
without getting anybody's funding or permission or anything.
من دون سماح للتمويل أو ما شابه من أي أحد.
So we started playing around with this.
فبدأنا بالتجارب على هذا.
And as we did it, we realized this was the basic problem --
و في خلال عملنا, استوعبنا أن هناك مشكلة أساسية--
that taking the sip of coffee --
أخذ رشفة من القهوة--
that there were humans doing this complicated process
يتطلب وجود أشخاص يقومون يهذه العملية المعقدة
and that what really needed to be done
و بهذا, ما احتجنا فعلا أن نقوم به,
was to automate this process like an assembly line
هو أتمتة العملية مثل خط انتاج
and build robots
و بناء رجال آليين
that would measure proteomics.
لكي يقيسوا البروتيوميات.
And so we did that,
و قد قمنا بذلك.
and working with David,
و عملت مع ديفيد,
we made a little company called Applied Proteomics eventually,
قمنا تدرجيا بإنشاء شركة صغيرة تدعى أبلايد بروتيوميات,
which makes this robotic assembly line,
التي تصنع خط انتاج آلي,
which, in a very consistent way, measures the protein.
هي , بطريقة شاملة, تقيس البروتين
And I'll show you what that protein measurement looks like.
و سأريكم ما هو شكل قياس البروتين.
Basically, what we do
أساسا, ما نعمله
is we take a drop of blood
هو أخذ نقطة من الدم
out of a patient,
من مريض,
and we sort out the proteins
و نفرز البروتينات
in the drop of blood
في نقطة الدم.
according to how much they weigh,
حسب مقدار وزنها,
how slippery they are,
و درجة سيولتها,
and we arrange them in an image.
و نرتبهم في صورة.
And so we can look at literally
و لنتستطيع النظر بحق إلى
hundreds of thousands of features at once
مئات الآلف من الصفات مرة واحدة
out of that drop of blood.
من تلك النقطة من الدم.
And we can take a different one tomorrow,
و نستطيع أخذ واحدة مختلفة غدا,
and you will see your proteins tomorrow will be different --
و نستطيع رؤية أن بروتين اليوم التالي ستكون مختلفة --
they'll be different after you eat or after you sleep.
ستخلف بعد أن تأكل و بعد أن تنام.
They really tell us what's going on there.
تخبرنا البروتينات فعلا ماذا يحدث هناك.
And so this picture,
و في هذه الصورة,
which looks like a big smudge to you,
التي تبدو كبقعة لك,
is actually the thing that got me really thrilled about this
هي حقا الشئ الذي جعلني مندهشا بهذا
and made me feel like we were on the right track.
و جعلني أشعر كأنني على خط السير الصحيح.
So if I zoom into that picture,
فإذا قربت هذه الصورة,
I can just show you what it means.
أستطيع أن أريكم ماذا تعني.
We sort out the proteins -- from left to right
نفرز البروتين-- من اليسار إلى اليمين
is the weight of the fragments that we're getting,
هو وزن الأجزاء التي حصلنا عليها.
and from top to bottom is how slippery they are.
و من الأعلى إلى الأسفل مدى سيولتها.
So we're zooming in here just to show you a little bit of it.
و نحن نقرب الصورة إلى هنا لنريك أن جزءا صغيرا منها.
And so each of these lines
و كل من هذه الخطوط
represents some signal that we're getting out of a piece of a protein.
تمثل نوعا من الإشارة التي تخرج من جزء من البروتين.
And you can see how the lines occur
و تستطيعون رؤية كيف تتشكل الخطوط
in these little groups of bump, bump, bump, bump, bump.
في هذه المجموعات الصغيرة خط، خط، خط، خط.
And that's because we're measuring the weight so precisely that --
و هذا لأننا نقيس الوزن بدقة شديدة بذلك--
carbon comes in different isotopes,
يأتي الكربون بعدة نظائر كيميائية،
so if it has an extra neutron on it,
بهذا اذا كان عليه نيوترون زائد،
we actually measure it as a different chemical.
فنحن فعلا نقيسه كمركب كيميائي مختلف.
So we're actually measuring each isotope as a different one.
فنحن فعلا نقيس كل نظير كيميائي كنظير مختلف عن الثاني.
And so that gives you an idea
و هذا يعطيكم فكرة
of how exquisitely sensitive this is.
عن الحساسية الفائقة لهذا.
So seeing this picture
برؤية هذه الصورة
is sort of like getting to be Galileo
مثل أن نكون جاليليو
and looking at the stars
و ننظر إلى النجوم
and looking through the telescope for the first time,
عبر التلسكوب للمرة الأولى،
and suddenly you say, "Wow, it's way more complicated than we thought it was."
و فجأة نقول "ياه، أنها أكثر تعقيدا بكثير عن ما كنا نظن."
But we can see that stuff out there
لكن نستطيع أن نرى الأشياء في الخارج
and actually see features of it.
و في الواقع نرى ميزاتها.
So this is the signature out of which we're trying to get patterns.
و بهذا إن نستطيع أن نستنتج من محاولنا إيجاد الأنماط.
So what we do with this
فماذا نفعل بهذا
is, for example, we can look at two patients,
هو، مثلا، نستطيع النظر إلى مريضين،
one that responded to a drug and one that didn't respond to a drug,
واحد استجاب لدواء و الآخر لم يستجيب لدواء،
and ask, "What's going on differently
و نسأل، " ما الذي اختلف
inside of them?"
داخلهم؟"
And so we can make these measurements precisely enough
فنستطيع أن نأخذ قياسات محددة كفاية
that we can overlay two patients and look at the differences.
لأن نطابق المريضين و ننظر إلى الاختلافات.
So here we have Alice in green
هنا لدينا أليس باللون الأخضر
and Bob in red.
و بوب بالأحمر.
We overlay them. This is actual data.
نطابقهم. هناك معلومات واقعية.
And you can see, mostly it overlaps and it's yellow,
و تستطيعون أن ترون، أغلبها تتطابق و إنها صفراء،
but there's some things that just Alice has
لكن هناك أشياء عند أليس فقط
and some things that just Bob has.
و أشياء عند بوب فقط.
And if we find a pattern of things
و إذا وجدنا نمط من الأشياء
of the responders to the drug,
المستجيبة للدواء،
we see that in the blood,
نراها في ذلك الدم،
they have the condition
لديها الحالة
that allows them to respond to this drug.
التي تمكنها من الاستجابة لهذا الدواء.
We might not even know what this protein is,
قد لا يمكننا معرفة ما هذا البروتين،
but we can see it's a marker
لكننا نستطيع رؤية أنه علامة
for the response to the disease.
للاستجابة للمرض.
So this already, I think,
لذلك إن هذا بالفعل، أظنه
is tremendously useful in all kinds of medicine.
نافع بشكل كبير في جميع أنواع الطب.
But I think this is actually
لكنني أظن أن هذا في الواقع
just the beginning
هو فقط البداية
of how we're going to treat cancer.
لكيف سنعالج السرطان.
So let me move to cancer.
دعوني انتقل إلى السرطان.
The thing about cancer --
الأمر في السرطان--
when I got into this,
عندما دخلت هذا المجال،
I really knew nothing about it,
لم أكن أعرف أي شئ عنه،
but working with David Agus,
لكن بالعمل مع ديفيد أوقس،
I started watching how cancer was actually being treated
بدأت بمشاهدة كيف في الواقع يعالج السرطان
and went to operations where it was being cut out.
و ذهبت إلى عمليات يقام فيها استئصاله.
And as I looked at it,
فعندما نظرت إليها،
to me it didn't make sense
لم يكن منطقيا بالنسبة لي
how we were approaching cancer,
كيف نتعامل مع السرطان.
and in order to make sense of it,
و لأصنع شيئا منطقيا منه،
I had to learn where did this come from.
علي أن أتعلم من أين أتى هذا.
We're treating cancer almost like it's an infectious disease.
نحن نعامل السرطان تقريبا كأنه مرض معدي.
We're treating it as something that got inside of you
نحن نعامله كالشىء الذي وصل بداخلنا
that we have to kill.
و علينا أن نقتله.
So this is the great paradigm.
فهذا هو النموذج الادراكي الكبير.
This is another case
إنها حالة أخرى
where a theoretical paradigm in biology really worked --
التي حقا نجحت فيها نظرية نموذج الإدراكي--
was the germ theory of disease.
هي نظرية جرثوم المرض.
So what doctors are mostly trained to do
فأغلب ما يدرب عليه الأطباء
is diagnose --
هو التشخيص --
that is, put you into a category
يعني تصنيفكم تحت فئة --
and apply a scientifically proven treatment
و تطبيق علاج أثبت علميا
for that diagnosis --
لذلك التشخيص.
and that works great for infectious diseases.
و هذا يعمل بشكل رائع للأمراض المعدية.
So if we put you in the category
فإذا وضعناكم في فئة
of you've got syphilis, we can give you penicillin.
لمن حصل لهم الزهري، نستطيع إعطائكم البنسلين.
We know that that works.
نعرف أنه يعمل.
If you've got malaria, we give you quinine
إذا أصابتكم الملاريا، نعطيكم الكينين،
or some derivative of it.
أو مشتق منها.
And so that's the basic thing doctors are trained to do,
و هذا هو الشئ الأساسي الذي يدرب عليه الأطباء.
and it's miraculous
و هو معجزة
in the case of infectious disease --
في حالة الأمراض المعدية--
how well it works.
يعمل بشكل جيد.
And many people in this audience probably wouldn't be alive
و يحتمل أن كثيرا من الناس في هذا الجمهور لم يكن ليصبحوا على قيد الحياة
if doctors didn't do this.
لو أن الأطباء لم يعملوا هذا.
But now let's apply that
الآن لنطبق هذا
to systems diseases like cancer.
لأمراض الأنظمة مثل السرطان.
The problem is that, in cancer,
المشكلة هي، في السرطان،
there isn't something else
أنه ليس هناك شئ
that's inside of you.
في داخلكم.
It's you; you're broken.
أنه أنتم، الذين كسرتم.
That conversation inside of you
تلك المحادثة في داخلكم
got mixed up in some way.
تخبطت بطريقة ما.
So how do we diagnose that conversation?
فكيف نشخص تلك المحادثة؟
Well, right now what we do is we divide it by part of the body --
حسنا الآن الذي نفعله هو أننا نقسمها حسب إجزاء الجسم--
you know, where did it appear? --
تعرفون، أين ظهرت--
and we put you in different categories
و نضعها في فئات مختلفة
according to the part of the body.
وفقا لأجزاء الجسم.
And then we do a clinical trial
و بعدها نقوم بالتجربة السريرية
for a drug for lung cancer
لعلاج سرطان الرئة
and one for prostate cancer and one for breast cancer,
و واحدة لسرطان البروستات و أخرى لسرطان الثدي،
and we treat these as if they're separate diseases
و نعالج هذه و كأنها أمراض مستقلة
and that this way of dividing them
و طريقة تقسيمهم هذه
had something to do with what actually went wrong.
كانت لها علاقة في الخطأ الذي حدث فعلا.
And of course, it really doesn't have that much to do
و بالطبع، لم تكن مؤثرة بشكل كبير
with what went wrong
في الخطأ الذي حصل.
because cancer is a failure of the system.
لأن السرطان هو فشل النظام.
And in fact, I think we're even wrong
و في واقع الأمر، أظن أننا مخطئون
when we talk about cancer as a thing.
عندما نتكلم عن السرطان كشئ.
I think this is the big mistake.
أظن أن هذه غلطة كبيرة.
I think cancer should not be a noun.
أظن أن السرطان لا يتوجب أن يكون أسما.
We should talk about cancering
يجب أن نتكلم عن السرطنة (فعل)
as something we do, not something we have.
كشئ نفعله، لا شئ نمتكله.
And so those tumors,
و هذه الأورام،
those are symptoms of cancer.
هي أعراض السرطان.
And so your body is probably cancering all the time,
و يحتمل أن أجسامكم تسرطن كل الوقت.
but there are lots of systems in your body
لكن هناك أنظمة كثيرة في أجسامكم
that keep it under control.
التي تسيطر عليها.
And so to give you an idea
و لأعطيكم فكرة
of an analogy of what I mean
مماثلة لما أقصد
by thinking of cancering as a verb,
في التفكير بالسرطان كفعل،
imagine we didn't know anything about plumbing,
تخيلوا أننا لم نعرف أي شىء عن السباكة،
and the way that we talked about it,
وطريقة تكلمنا عنها،
we'd come home and we'd find a leak in our kitchen
لنحضر إلى المنزل و نجد تسرب في المطبخ
and we'd say, "Oh, my house has water."
و سنقول، " اه، منزلي فيه ماء"
We might divide it -- the plumber would say, "Well, where's the water?"
و قد نقسمه-- السباك سيقول، "حسنا أين الماء؟"
"Well, it's in the kitchen." "Oh, you must have kitchen water."
"حسنا، أنه في المطبخ." "اه، إنه ماء من المطبخ."
That's kind of the level at which it is.
هذا نوع المستوى الذي هو عليه.
"Kitchen water,
"ماء مطبخ؟
well, first of all, we'll go in there and we'll mop out a lot of it.
حسنا، قبل كل شىء، لنذهب إلى هناك و نمسح الكثير منه
And then we know that if we sprinkle Drano around the kitchen,
و نعرف أننا إذا رشينا دراينو (منتج يزيل الانسداد في المجاري) في أنحاء المطبخ،
that helps.
فإنه يساعد.
Whereas living room water,
في حين أن ماء غرفة المعيشة،
it's better to do tar on the roof."
الأفضل له هو وضع القار على السقف."
And it sounds silly,
و قد يبدو هذا سخيفا،
but that's basically what we do.
لكن هذا هو ما فعلا نقوم به.
And I'm not saying you shouldn't mop up your water if you have cancer,
و أنا لا أقول أنه لا يتوجب عليكم مسح الأرض إذا كان لديكم السرطان.
but I'm saying that's not really the problem;
لكن ما أقوله هو أنه ليست عن فعلا المشكلة
that's the symptom of the problem.
لكن أعراض المشكلة.
What we really need to get at
هي التي توجب علينا أن نصل إليها
is the process that's going on,
أنها العملية التي تحدث،
and that's happening at the level
و التي تحدث على مستوى
of the proteonomic actions,
أفعال و تواصل البروتينات
happening at the level of why is your body not healing itself
الحاصلة على مستوى عدم قدرة الجسم لعلاج نفسه
in the way that it normally does?
كما في عادته؟
Because normally, your body is dealing with this problem all the time.
لكن في العادة اجسامنا تتعامل مع هذه المشكلة في كل الأوقات
So your house is dealing with leaks all the time,
و بيوتكم تتعامل مع التسرب في كل الأوقات
but it's fixing them. It's draining them out and so on.
لكن إصلاحهم. هو تجفيفهم و من ذلك القبيل.
So what we need
فما نحتاجه
is to have a causative model
هو أن يكون لدينا نموذج للمسببات
of what's actually going on,
لما يحصل فعلا،
and proteomics actually gives us
و البروتيوميات التي تنتج لنا
the ability to build a model like that.
القدرة على بناء نموذج مثل هذا.
David got me invited
ديفيد حصل لي على دعوة
to give a talk at National Cancer Institute
لأعطي محاضرة في معهد السرطان الدولي
and Anna Barker was there.
و آنا باركر كانت هناك.
And so I gave this talk
فأعطيت هذه المحاضرة
and said, "Why don't you guys do this?"
و قلت. "لما تقومون بهذا؟"
And Anna said,
و آنا قالت،
"Because nobody within cancer
"لأن لا أحد في مجال السرطان
would look at it this way.
ينظر إليه بهذه الطريقة.
But what we're going to do, is we're going to create a program
لكن ما سنعمله هو، إنه سنقوم بعمل برنامج
for people outside the field of cancer
للأشخاص الذين خارج مجال السرطان
to get together with doctors
ليجتمعوا مع الأطباء
who really know about cancer
الذين حقا يعرفون الكثير عن السرطان
and work out different programs of research."
و يعملون على برامج مختلفة من الأبحاث."
So David and I applied to this program
فقدمنا أنا و ديفيد على هذا البرنامج
and created a consortium
و أنشأنا إئتلاف تجاري
at USC
في جامعة جنوب كلايفورنيا
where we've got some of the best oncologists in the world
حيث يوجد لدينا أفصل أطباء الأورام في العالم
and some of the best biologists in the world,
و بعض أفضل علماء الأحياء في العالم،
from Cold Spring Harbor,
من كولد سبرنج هاربر،
Stanford, Austin --
ستانفورد، أستن--
I won't even go through and name all the places --
لن أقوم حتى بالمرور على أسماء كل الأماكن
to have a research project
لأحصل على مشروع بحث
that will last for five years
ليستمر خمس سنوات
where we're really going to try to build a model of cancer like this.
حيث سنقوم فعلا ببناء نموذج للسرطان مثل هذا.
We're doing it in mice first,
سنفعله في الفئران أولا.
and we will kill a lot of mice
و سنقتل الكثير من الفئران
in the process of doing this,
في انجاز هذا،
but they will die for a good cause.
لكنهم سيموتون من أجل سبب جيد.
And we will actually try to get to the point
و نحن نحاول بالفعلا الوصول إلى نقطة
where we have a predictive model
يكون لدينا فيها نظام تنبؤ
where we can understand,
حيث نستطيع فهم،
when cancer happens,
متى يحصل السرطان،
what's actually happening in there
ما يحصل حقا فيه،
and which treatment will treat that cancer.
و أي علاج سيعالج ذلك السرطان.
So let me just end with giving you a little picture
دعوني انهي هذا بإعطائكم صورة صغيرة
of what I think cancer treatment will be like in the future.
لما سيكون عليه علاج السرطان في المستقبل.
So I think eventually,
فأظن أنه تدريجيا،
once we have one of these models for people,
حين يكون لدينا واحد من هذه النماذج للناس،
which we'll get eventually --
التي سنصل إليها تدريجيا --
I mean, our group won't get all the way there --
أقصد، مجتموعتنا لن تصل إليه كله --
but eventually we'll have a very good computer model --
لكن تدريجيا سيصبح لدينا نموذج جيد على الحاسوب
sort of like a global climate model for weather.
مثل نموذج المناخ العالمي للأجواء.
It has lots of different information
لديها معلومات كثيرا مختلفة
about what's the process going on in this proteomic conversation
عن ما هي العملية التي تجري في محادثات البروتيوميات
on many different scales.
على مقاييس كثيرة مختلفة.
And so we will simulate
و بهذا سنقوم بمحاكاة
in that model
في هذا النموذج
for your particular cancer --
نوعا معينا من السرطان--
and this also will be for ALS,
و هذا سيكون أيضا للأي أل أس،
or any kind of system neurodegenerative diseases,
أو لأي نظام من أمراض خسارة خاصية النيورنات
things like that --
أشياء من هذا القبيل
we will simulate
ستقوم بمحاكاة
specifically you,
بالخصوص أنتم
not just a generic person,
ليس شخصا عاما،
but what's actually going on inside you.
لكن ما يحصل بداخلكم.
And in that simulation, what we could do
و في هذه المحاكاة، ما نستطيع عمله
is design for you specifically
هو التصميم لكم بالتحديد
a sequence of treatments,
سلسلة من العلاج،
and it might be very gentle treatments, very small amounts of drugs.
و قد يكون علاج خفيفا، كمية قليلة من الدواء.
It might be things like, don't eat that day,
قد يكون أشياء مثل لا تأكلون هذا اليوم
or give them a little chemotherapy,
أو أعطيهم بعض من العلاج الكميائي،
maybe a little radiation.
قد يكون القليل من الاشعاع.
Of course, we'll do surgery sometimes and so on.
و بالطبع، سنعمل القليل من الجراحة بعض الأحيان و من هذا القبيل.
But design a program of treatments specifically for you
لكن تصميم برنامج لكم بالتحديد
and help your body
و مساعدة أجسامكم
guide back to health --
لنقودها إلى صحتها--
guide your body back to health.
نقود أجسامكم إلى صحتها.
Because your body will do most of the work of fixing it
لأن أجسامكم ستقوم بغالبية العمل لاصلاحها
if we just sort of prop it up in the ways that are wrong.
لو فقط جعلناها تعمل بالطرق الخطأ.
We put it in the equivalent of splints.
نضعها في المكافئ من الجبائر.
And so your body basically has lots and lots of mechanisms
و الجسم أساسا لديه الكثير الكثير من المكينيكيات
for fixing cancer,
لاصلاح السرطان
and we just have to prop those up in the right way
لكن يجب علينا أن نفعلها بالطريقة الصحيحة
and get them to do the job.
و نجعلها تقوم بوظيفتها.
And so I believe that this will be the way
فأنا أعتقد أنه ستكون هذه الطريقة
that cancer will be treated in the future.
التي يعالج فيها السرطان بالمستقبل.
It's going to require a lot of work,
ستتطلب الكثير من العمل،
a lot of research.
الكثير من البحث.
There will be many teams like our team
سيكون هناك الكثير من الفرق مثل فريقنا
that work on this.
يعملون على هذا.
But I think eventually,
أظن أننا تدريجيا،
we will design for everybody
سنصمم للكل
a custom treatment for cancer.
علاجا خاصا للسرطان.
So thank you very much.
شكرا جزيلا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)